hello and welcome everyone this is
active inference guest stream
72.1 it's March 1st 2024 and we're here
with autom meta alignment lab AI so
welcome please feel free to introduce
yourself and kick it off and we'll take
it from
there
unmute and then go from
there yeah it would be really good if I
if I did unmute for thanks I appreciate
the uh the introduction um my name is
Austin I run alignment lab
AI we kind of build out in the open
source and aim at least I personally we
aim for kind of Building Solutions to
problems before we have to deal with
impacts I think um in general it's
probably pretty important that this AI
thing goes about as well as we can get
it to go for
everyone um I think it's it's really
important you know there's there's quite
a lot of uh there's quite a lot of
outcomes man that we can really get from
all this because I can say with with a
lot of confidence from the inside that
the rabbit hole really just keep going
deeper when you start to look into the
stuff
and it it's meaningful because the rate
that things are moving right now is not
a temporary thing we're I really I don't
think that we're moving as fast as we're
going to be before it's all over said
and done uh and it's a good thing
because so far hugely positive impacts
from my
perspective I think yeah I think that
like overall it if it's going this well
this long I mean we're a year in it's
going to be it looks better and better
every day I think for the way that
things are
tur okay so many places to jump in a
year from what better according to what
oh fair you know a year from GPT
Prometheus bringing us the fires of
Olympus and infinite free data um to
train whatever kind of model we want uh
I think that's really the big thing that
uh that's happened is this the the the
performative use of language by the
models really allows for this nice kind
of gluey Middle Ground to build data
sets out for different use cases just by
saying that you want them um because
prior most things you needed to build
classifiers by hand from scratch
and that alone is just one step of a
larger Pipeline and I think that that is
a barrier that's like no longer there
for like a lot of things which is
nice okay let's take a step back and
then reapo what were you working on as
you turn to language models or how did
you get into this
space so so I've always had a I guess
you could say like a bit of an obsessive
nature um and I've always had a lot of
involvement in my life
with complex and challenging things uh
and at the time I was just getting into
like image models and pythia and the
earlier llms before llama really leaked
out and that was when I first started to
take the space like very seriously I had
dabbled a little bit and done a few
little projects like Tex to speech
models and things of that nature
beforehand U but when the gpc4 came out
and I was messing with the original
version of that model when it first came
out that was like a very different
experience and I definitely stayed up
for like a couple of days messing with
it um when it first came I had like a
100 messages every three hours you could
talk to it for and it like it was so
much slower back then that was plenty
and
uh I don't know I just thought it was
really fascinating and then I just kept
doing it and then I started making money
doing it and so I just just kept doing
it harder and uh since then I think all
the original people that I first met up
with in the open source we still all
talk to each other and we just kind of
fell in together because that's just
what happens I think when you're doing
it for
free okay again a lot of uh places to go
but maybe give a little bit of an
overview for those who have or haven't
worked on open source software or
projects like what does it really mean
for one of these models to be open
Source are there different senses that
people are using
it yeah
um so largely everyone's in the open
source is it's pretty it's a weird split
between machine learning engineers and
people using it for like formal academic
reasons and then people grabbing a lot
of the newer models just to use them and
have their own use cases and play with
agent pipelines I think that it's it's
going to be really interesting when we
start to get to a place where the
tooling has gotten there to allow for
people to just use the agents and it's
going to have like a lot of impacts that
are super cool because once you can do
it a little bit you know it seems like
everything that I've sort of pushed at
in this space um a little bit of
progress turns into a lot really really
quickly because like as soon as you can
do it well one time you get a great data
set and that lets other people iterate
on it and then everyone works together
and the open source typically so it
moves things pretty quickly um I have a
hard time like kind of identifying
though from the outside what what
exactly the uh the big appeal is to
people who aren't obsessed with it aside
from the fact that's like very sci-fi so
like that at least I know for a fact
isn't temporary at least in my case I
think it's still
sci-fi can
um yeah can can I ask if uh if you've
had much of a chance to get really uh
really deep into anything like that
yourself as far as dealing with the
models directly
or I think we have our own brand of
active inference sci-fi speculative
futurism Etc and also though I have used
local and cloudbased language
models yeah I think it's going to be
really fascinating too when people start
to access the lower level stuff because
the llms are really interesting but the
use cases are way narrow because they're
so big right I think things like
classifiers and linear progression
models which are just very tiny models
that you train on your CPU to do very
specific tasks people really don't
realize that you're still getting that
same kind of weird gooey generativist
with with smaller models except you also
just get to do it really really fast on
a CPU and get 100% accuracy and so that
has like a huge amount of benefits for
the businesses stuff too it's like it's
things where it's really hard to code
really easy to train a model for I think
um it's hard to say that like
man yeah there's there's very few
Industries I think that AR going to
really be impacted we're so embedded
with digital stuff you
know how would you say this is different
than just doing statistics on
computers I mean it is isn't it
it's that's an interesting question so
the the long answer or the short answer
is that it is it's just statistics on
computers the I think the more
interesting short answer though is the
statistics on computers
is very similar to statistics on brains
I think it's very similar
to uh non-deterministic systems it's
it's stuff
that we don't understand the individual
nuanced interactions but you get a lot
of information at a higher level that
you don't have to actually do all the
work of understanding every single
individual thing about it and so being
able to do that that on a computer in a
way that is so robust that you can do it
you know many billions of times really
quickly is something
where the limitation becomes how clever
are you about approaching a problem
because like now you have the option to
not even know how it works and train a
model to identify patterns and noise and
just figure it out for you and uh yeah I
think that's going to become cooler and
cooler the smaller and smaller the model
get because like I've never seen
anything get smaller and stronger at the
same time over and over and over again
like I had for this last year so
I us having models at home to me looks
like a foregone conclusion and that's
really
cool yeah okay yeah to the statistics on
computers I mean it's always been a joke
about machine learning and such that it
is just under the hood statistics and a
linear aggression yes you can go from
observations to the line of best fit and
also you can generate synthetic data
from a linear aggression so what has
been occurring to facilitate the
expansion across modalities so
ferociously is this related to
computational Resource accessibility to
what extent does this have to do with
architectural
changes so it's pretty easy to get if
you think of it from a like the
standpoint of like
your task to go make a model that's
multimodal and then also from the
standpoint if you want to use any AI
right if you want to use something and
you're just going to interact with it
naturally because the best thing that we
could do with these llms is have this
very natural way of interacting back and
forth for interfaces or whatever thing
um we're not we're not text based right
like we have faces and voices and
tonality and all these other things and
so the use case Cas is pretty clear and
then from the development side it's much
much easier to build a data set that's
multimodal once you have one multimodal
model you know once you have an llm that
can see a picture now you can just build
as many data sets as you want to make as
many llm see pictures as you want if you
don't have that you have pictures and
now you have to get captions on a
million of them it's much harder to
do um so it's like an iterative process
and you know especially if you notice
this the the vision language models
although we did have lava um aside from
that and like Lavar which is lion's uh
version of lava basically it's just
another iteration on the same
thing what option did we have before gbt
4V to really build these large scale
Vision language data sets for these
models to become multimodal and
conversational at the same time um
Alibaba actually did us a huge favor too
not intentionally but they made um but
yeah it was was intentionally it was an
open source release they released a
quint audio which is very similar to
Lava as well it's except it's audio in
language which means we don't have to
build tons and tons of little
classifiers to go run over audio data to
label it for us and just tell it what to
do and telling it what to do is much
much easier and like that's the cool
thing right like that is the benefit of
these huge llms you just tell them what
to do
beautiful so it's often remarked upon
that there's a next token prediction in
in play here so coming from the
engineering side how do you understand
that because in the active inference
space in predictive processing there is
a lot of discussion around prediction
and real-time prediction the role in
cognition but just coming from an
engineering side like how did it come to
be that predicting the next token became
so entrenched as a mechanism to generate
even structures that have long-term
structure so you can think of it as far
as like what's going the hood it it
really is very similar to just a search
I mean it's very similar to the exact
same thing that you're doing when you're
doing like text completion on your phone
and it's finishing the word for you but
in order to model like statistically
model systems that are
complex you have to actually model the
features that you can derive from those
systems so when I say a sentence and I
get a response and that response is
coherent the only way to predict that
coherent response is by operating on the
logic that's implicit in the sentence
that I out that I gave right and so you
do have this kind of higher level sort
of meaning that comes out of strings of
tokens even though they are selected
just based on their
likelihood um and whether or not that's
that's something that we're just
inputting like imposing over the
responses or the models coming up with
because it really understands I think is
more philosophical than um a uh a matter
of
engineering that being
said letters aren't meaning and language
has restrictions and there's really
tokens can only be used in so many ways
and so likely it's a really inefficient
way to do that if uh if
indeed I mean not even if indeed that is
what we're doing right like the whole
reason the language models are good is
because we like that when they talk it
makes sense and um we could be doing
that better you know there there's
probably I mean Kathy actually just made
a post about this on Twitter I think
talking about how tokens really are a
huge issue I think it's true it's really
restrictive
um so
can sorry I'm like I'm like distracted
because in the back of my head I'm
thinking about uh about active Ence
and you know real time kind of reactive
modeling of these of these these systems
because I
think that then becomes a sort of meta
layer on top of that right where you
have a um where you have a
uh sorry my dog over here you have a um
wow I totally lost my entire train
but when you're actually modeling
systems in real time that's different
right because what Transformers are
doing is finishing a string it's
stateless if you run to inferences on a
regular model like an llm like
everyone's used to those two sentences
will be the exact same sentence both
times if you don't have literally a
random number generator right to
convolute and turn into a new one to do
that I think in real time is like not
it's not even part of the equation right
because reality is never the same thing
twice so you start to be able to
interact I think with very complex
systems and in that is just good data to
model them just because there's nothing
else to model when you have data at that
granularity
yeah well that makes me think about how
the temperature and the noise that has
to get injected in there's this path of
least action the path of most likely
continuation that has to be
stochastically or pseud randomly broken
in order to get out of
valleys and so for models where we have
total observability and control pseudo
Randomness has to be reinjected or
generated endogenously whereas just like
you described for the organism in its
engagement with the
niche it is getting fuzzed by reality
continually and so that is a very
different setting and um when there is a
realtime precarious
engagement it opens the door to
extremely different kinds of knowledge
and repres representation and
adaptivity um for example in the active
inference partially observable Markov
decision process type models all of the
ways that the world changes get encoded
in a transition Matrix but there isn't
necessarily any representation of like
overall trajectories more like sort of
flows and next moments and gradients and
so there's a really interesting um
tension between what is
explainable with digital or synthetic
intelligence and with bi
ological and it's like explainable to
who or what part would make it
explainable or
understandable because even when we
understand the whole linear aggression
or the whole Transformer
architecture there are
still it's almost like it's all there
it's like if you knew all the
ingredients of dinner would you have
understood
dinner yeah it's it becomes abstract the
closer that you that you look just
because the complexity is so high right
like when when you're looking at systems
like Transformers it's like very very
many small decisions that happen very
very quickly and I do think it does
become arbitrary at some scale because
like I also don't know exactly what's
happening in my CPU at like the electron
level right like I don't know what all
the individual bits and bites are doing
underneath my computer um what's
interesting I think is to
consider if modeling this landscape
that's entirely different but all of the
information is reactive then all of the
data is no longer human data like it is
right now where we train the models just
basically on the internet right it's all
human expression Which models humans
really really well but if you're not
doing that and instead you're just
modeling everything where you're
modeling is real life and I think that
uh to oh my gosh I apologize hey get out
of here go on
when you're modeling real life and
you're getting feedback from real life
the only way that goes is to improve I
mean if you're building a system which
is effective at iterating until it can
make some progress the hard part then
becomes defining what the progress is
how do I tell when I'm doing a good
thing right because for me to do that
with an llm I now have to Define things
I don't understand things that are
bigger than me if I'm trying to L like
larly improve in all cases which is
become this weird goal post I think with
llms um because we H now we have many
many many benchmarks for many many many
tens of thousands of examples and like
that still really doesn't do it because
you can't simulate real life in real
life so feedback from reality hugely
important it's reinforcement
learning sort of right
like it although I think that term has
become kind of vague too now that
everything's kind of cut and fuzz
together as the scales have gone
up well I'll just say a key difference
between reinforcement learning and
active inference you frame the challenge
as um how do I know when good things
happen and the reinforcement learning
answer is well we'll propose this reward
function such that there's better and
worse on this scale and then we will
pursue policies or observations that are
better up in terms of how warding there
are will reinforce what works on this
second level ad hoc proposed W function
then to get to another piece of what you
said things I don't understand and
basically learning opportunity that has
to get shoehorned into that reward
function somehow with like curiosity
bonuses all these different techniques
that people have developed so in
contrast to active inference we're doing
direct optimization on the generative
model such that rather than defining
like body temperature as reward in and
then pursuing reward we Define body
temperature at homeostasis as expected
and then pursue what's expected so that
gives a direct measure of how well
things are going in terms of how
expected things are going and it gives a
direct measure of things that are being
learned or not understood in terms of
epistemic value so it's not quite at
least in the open source space applied
at the scales that a lot of the models
that you've been mentioning are however
that's what excites us every day
is that in principle there's a simpler
and a physics grounded first principles
approach to address some of these exact
questions about like agents and their
autonomous engagement with a
niche yeah I think
um I think that anything is better than
what we're doing now absolutely sure I
think that if you have like a baseline
by which you can start from and you're
measuring variants in that Baseline
agnostic to the kind kind of human
perception of good and bad then you do
just kind of set a floor right and all
you're doing is really raising the floor
incrementally
because
inherently there's stochasticity in the
system and the stochasticity produces
higher quality and lower quality so if
you have a floor anything below that
quality you can just throw away and now
you've got a means of improvement that
you can derive formally which is way way
more real than what we do with llms
which is kind of guess
and then into it and we just sort of try
stuff and train it on only the good
until it it's seen enough to do that
really well um because like really that
kind of system it's insane that it
actually got to the scale of modeling
language really well because I mean if
any of that just speaks to human like
creativity or Ingenuity or something
because what that's for is for labels
right or like assigning a
value it it is I mean it's cool that we
can do that it's also wildly expensive
and there's no way this is efficient at
all you know the the these models are
shrinking really fast in spite of the
fact that we're have like we're just
kind of like this might work better and
then it does that uh that that's not
going to last and if that's the case
with llms with all of their inherent
they have these giant limitations in
every direction like Transformers in
particular then everything else can
probably go the other direction too just
get denser and um that to me is also
really fascinating it's the questions
then like
what can you start to do with that if
you can imagine some sci-fi scenario
wherein now you've got networks of
models that are very very small and
they're very very performative you can
start to build systems that are very
complicated for cheap and cheap is
important because money right now is
kind of in charge of how quickly all the
Technologies
move and I think uh yeah having some
system by which you can take these many
many small systems and derive sort of
group performance enhancements without
having to Define group performance
enhancements in a way that is
purely I mean it's just formally
understood it takes away all the
weirdness with llms because those are
not formally understood like you can't
derive what a qualitative Improvement is
because it's qualitatively all human
data it's just
biased if that made any sense at all I
might have gone in circle there yeah
interesting well it makes me think of
the the large and
monolithic nature of the current models
um and yet inside of them are defined
smaller computational entities like a
node in a graph that takes in some
stimuli and then outputs um or another
change or outputs an activation
variously and this is a common theme in
active inference which is like you can
have a more monolithic like
representation of a cognitive system and
then you can all that's like a top down
descriptor like the ant colony as a unit
in terms of its foraging distribution
and then there's also the bottom up that
describes multiple smaller autonomous
components and how their interactions
with each other with the niche the
ecosystem of shared intelligence how
that comes to be one and the same as the
view from the top and so it is
interesting that as more
ways like tall buildings with small
Pebbles small buildings with large
Pebbles and all these different
combinations of different um
computational components but now that
state space is massive in terms of the
compositional space of
models even before parameterizing them
or touching data just the simple
architectural so how do people think
about that kind of structure
learning and meta
learning in what ways do you think that
there are gains with like showing a
vision recognizing AI like showing it
images and having it update making a
kind of closed loop with image
generation
enclosure or even critiquing its own
[Music]
architecture okay
so the I mean if you're trying to see if
there is a
limitation as far
as how much of a representation you can
fit into a mod like how dense can they
get or how how non-d dense can they be
they could be infinitely non-d dense
but it doesn't actually seem from my
perspective like there is much of a
limitation beyond the amount of time
you're willing to wait and the amount of
data that you have
the
actual you know
functional components of the logic by
which the models gain or lose
performance along whatever metric that
is that you
decide is it seems almost unrelated
because it comes down to the question
really then becomes like well how
complex can a thing be and how much
variance can you fit into this element
and I'm sure you can probably find some
sort of maximal state of compression
but whatever that is it's it feels like
it's very AR because we haven't started
to slow down on how small the models can
get and they do just keep getting as
dense with no breaks so I
think as far as like self
feedback that's that's like a that's
even that is also like another layer of
kind of efficiency that could be gained
there because you don't really even then
have to store things in the model if
you're storing it in kind of a social
exchange or or some kind of back and
forth um there was a paper earlier last
year like it was it was something camel
I think is the name of the model and
that was kind of like a clock and it was
just two models inferencing back and
forth and Performing hnte tasks by
keeping themselves in line that way and
it is like a step of getting around this
sort of stateless behavior that the llms
have implicitly I think that this is
probably an element um in at least some
sense
for any kind of architecture which is
going to involve Transformers and still
have a linear kind of progressive
interaction with
things but I think you have to be really
clever uh I certainly don't think that
you should be have the model feedback on
itself and train on it unless you're
doing that many times quite a convoluted
way because you're just going to get a
model that gets very stylistically
whatever you decided was a good thing to
train itself on for an llm anyways but
is storing information I guess in re in
like the logic of the systems rather
than in the weights of the models I
think is a good place to uh is a good
place to look at if you're if you're
trying to solve that
problem okay shifting a little bit you
wanted to call this open- Source AI the
truth is the first casualty in War what
is
happening well um we're at War because I
I really just wanted a pretty dramatic
title to the video so that I could get
people to look at it because the the
thing about the open source man is that
it looks really really good from the
outside right now like if you're
engaging with it it looks very vibrant
and there's many thousands of models and
the leaderboards are shifting around
every single day and people are engaging
and companies are getting funded and
it's the exact same number of people
there was a year ago and those models
are all the same models moving back and
forth and none of that funding is
hitting people who are in the open
source some of it is that's not true so
like some people are definitely getting
funding I think that like like news just
got
funded um I think that it's really more
of our fault than anyone's
because I think dude it's really hard to
do a UI and do HTML and CSS when you can
go do AI
instead and if you're doing HDML in CSS
it is much harder to go be inspired to
work for free for a long
time and so that that that gets bridged
right like that so that's I think that's
really mostly what this Market thing is
but narrative is important and
um especially now because we're not like
out of the weeds you know I think that
it's very much either taken way too
seriously or not seriously enough at all
this idea of
like where Do We Go From Here what does
it look like in a year
and what are everyone arguing about
right because there's noise in the space
and there's people talking about AGI and
everyone's kind of scared because the
technology is moving really really fast
it's really hard to understand
and AGI and being scared and arguing
about it
is the only thing that is really
truly potentially going to have the
consequences I think because like in
both cases it's like your own best
interests are not being
served um because all that needs to
happen for the people who are very like
scared is they just uh like access to
this really dense opaque wall of
whatever we're talking about you know um
because it's not it's not really scary
once you look at it you kind of get it
and it just kind of is shocking at first
and people aren't used to things moving
fast and that's really most of it um and
AGI is I mean we're not even there it's
been a I can say for a fact it's been a
year we've made 0% progress so it's AGI
open AI is marketing when they're
talking about AGI no one's got AGI no
one's
there in the right
direction I
promise it's uh no it's it's narrative
and it's argumentation and it's
political and money and it's the same
thing that's always been except this
time like we really can't mess around
too much because like we have a chance
of enabling people to have access
to all of the like understanding that
we've compiled like as a species on the
internet and in books and in each other
and you know you can do a lot with that
and you can really improve your life
substantially and be free of a lot of
the stuff we deal with a lot of the
manipulation that we get from other
people other companies other whatevers
and we could also just totally drop the
ball and we could just Center all of
this on like five guys and they could
just through even through no fault of
their
own damage the social structure that we
exist in I mean this has already
happened and the nature of the Beast is
that AI is is opaque and it's very hard
to understand and the first thing that
we ever did with it in the markets was
use it to manipulate people's behaviors
without them knowing they're interacted
with this is what the bubble is and the
algorithm you know um whenever you see
two people online and they're just both
ridiculous because they're both Total
Polar Opposites because they're both
taking like baby's first take about
whatever topic that's recommender
systems you know that was that was
optimization for engagement that was
unsupervised and so they people just
didn't know that was happening and they
were making money so they didn't really
look too hard and um that's something
that can go away and like these kind of
problems can be dealt
with as long as we're the signal of
noise ratio stays good and the utility
stays focused on
um but yeah I guess that's what I mean
when I say like the truth is a first
casualty in war it's because like don't
get disillusioned it looks good because
it's like it just looks good you know
there it's not bad but like it's not the
open source isn't improving just because
people are doing stuff you know what I
mean because like the things that people
are doing is just stuff it's not uh it's
not all negative it's quite positive but
you should do more join in the open
source I'll give you free stuff we do it
all the time it's
great um I Heard autom meta wants you I
heard nothing to fear about AGI but fear
of AGI itself I think you called it like
you saw it I mean what is
truth that's a tough question I think
that
the it's oh man to to take a very famous
quote that might be kind of funny if you
recognize it I know it when I see
it how do you recognize it or know it or
know that you know it when you see
it maybe you don't right that's the
problem I think if it's a person and
you're talking to a person that's that's
pretty easy that's at least doable
Maybe
you can fit really good patterns well I
think with AI and I don't think that
anyone is doing
this but the potential is there to
certainly uh manipulate people in a way
that's very
very very hard for them to detect at
very large scales for very cheap um but
I think that it's less important
to highlight that in particular right
now just because we have so many more
fundamental things that we should deal
with first because like that problem
solves itself uh and when I say it
solves itself I mean to say
that those systems which do exist exist
sanss the people intending to make that
right so it's always accidental when
there's going to be consequences from
those kinds of things and the accidents
are going to be largely because someone
set it up and then they left and then
other people ran it and they just put
kept putting money into it and then it
just was G
and uh these these are just going to
become robust I mean there's no way it
doesn't because like it's emphasized now
and it's becoming more and more
important and generative systems are no
longer really being relegated to a thing
that runs on a CPU in the server room
and no one touches it it's all becoming
interconnected with everyone's pipelines
because now this is starting to very
clearly become like the middle of what
everyone's doing because even if you're
not in the AI space as an AI company
you're still a company you're still
dealing with data
and you'd rather talk to it than code it
um so we're in luck there uh
but the truth I think is up to you
really if uh if you want to take a
philosophical note on it I think you
should be able to choose right and
that's what alignment really is um it's
not really some moral sort of framework
that you decide for other
people it's it's you have a tool and the
tool does tool stuff and it doesn't
blackmail your
grandma blinded
so I guess autometa says don't Blackmail
My
grandma okay totally noted where do you
see alignment in relationship or tension
with other virtues that people
have I don't think it is that's that's
the thing is like it's it's not
fundamentally it's if it is then it's
not alignment that's the whole point
it's not even a complicated thing it's
it really shouldn't even be
controversial because the truth of the
matter is something that's aligned
is something that does what you think it
does when you think it does that and it
does it every time isn't that just
cility I don't know I don't really think
of it like that I mean I just think of
it like a tool right right now I mean
maybe in the future that might be cility
I think probably not anytime soon I
think we'll have a lot more uh kind of
pragmatic discussions before socially we
decide how we're going to arrange
ourselves on that front and we'll
probably have a lot of leadup time to
get
there uh I
think I think it is compelling though it
Bears mentioning
like the ability to model language like
in a very good way with
Statistics is compelling to people
especially if they don't really know
what's going on under the hood and I
don't mean that to say that it becomes
boring once you look under the hood it
becomes more interesting
but once you do and you do kind of
understand what's going on it's like oh
yeah clearly this thing is not alive
this is a trick right like it's a search
engine
and when you don't do that though and
especially if your first interaction
because like right now there's not too
many entry points and you just have Chad
gbt and Chad gbt very much acknowledges
that it's an AI all the time and it has
like a very it has a personality like a
very strict set of behaviors which it
responds to deterministically given the
right kind of inputs and it feels
regular and I that gives people the
impression that they're all like this
and that it's nonhumans sounding nature
as it is now which is intentionally
implemented by the way so that it
doesn't so that you can't use it to like
fool people and and impersonate anyone
because the truth is like they're
actually really good at that you can
actually get really really natural
behavior out of the models right now
and don't get tricked I guess is all I'm
trying to say because it's it's just
compelling but you keep messing with
them you give it about a month man and
you mess with every day you're going by
the end of that month you're you're G to
get it like it's it's there's a spark in
the eye and then there's like glass
behind it you know what I
mean with llms as they are presently
anyways I feel like you might have been
uh aiming at a different point and I
walk right past it
yeah not specifically but that's an
interesting way to say it um what about
the participation in the open source
component I mean what are the actual
touch points to be involved and how has
that you know where do you see that
really working and how does it become
accessible procedurally and as a
networking Community not just as an API
that gets provided to some
people sure I mean
there is an implicit technical
complexity if you want to get low level
but man that's true of everything it's
technology if you just want to use a
model like that's not as bad as it looks
that's that one's pretty easy um you
might have to read a read me or two in
GitHub and I know it's still in GitHub
we don't have too many good websites but
it's because I have to host the model so
I'm gonna give you a website and you got
to pay me and like it's not really open
source anymore you know because like how
someone can hold gpus up but you go to
like you can go get the Aphrodite engine
or uh the text generation web UI or one
of a few I mean there's there's quite a
few inference engines now where you can
just pick the model from hugging face
and hugging face is like GitHub it's
just a website where you go and there
are models uploaded and data sets
uploaded and you can they have this
fantastic coding library that makes it
really easy for guys like me to code
everything on the backs side so that you
can just click a button and put in the
name of the model and then it just works
and uh that's an easy way to get started
I mean if you want to talk about like
Comm
how do you engage it's mostly on Discord
which is weird but like there there's
probably a whole bunch of reasons for
that that I don't personally understand
because I'm not a huge fan of Discord
but go on there and like every major
company that's in the open source and
every group and organization they all
have their own Discord a lot of it's on
slack uh Twitter I mean likely if you're
here watching this video probably you
kind of know where to look um the cool
thing is all of the inroads to the open
source are the same kind of network so
you can just like slide right in kind of
in any Comm Cal like pigmans Community
mine you know
[Music]
um and the tenor of it is very much
follow your interest I mean the bloke
himself is uh technium are like both
Titans on this front of connected to
everybody Community is sort of just
generally AI is cool both extremely
performative so the best stuff is always
like right in front of them because they
just put it there I think it's a good
way to
go um hugging face in general
though what surprised you the most so
far in this
year oh man just like every 10 minutes
like on that yeah like I can't even
answer that because it's like I'm in a
constant state of shock
like yeah I don't think humans are made
for things that move this fast open AI
just bought uh that company that's
making the humanoid robots um
01 right so they got a robot and they're
like hey guys we're making humanoid
robots like cool and then it's like
month later hey look they're folding
clothes and stacking boxes Isn't that
cool and it's like yeah now we have
billions of dollars we're going right
open
AI micros I mean yeah it's so fast like
everything is moving so quickly it's
really interesting and cool I'm quite
excited
I still think it I think it still might
be like a media thing I'm not I'm not a
th% sure we're about to get robots it'd
be cool if did though I wouldn't be too
upset by it but probably it's a cost
thing if anything it's a lot of
Hardware given the speed and the
intensity and the novelty even when
you're
in have you seen anything or do you have
any thoughts on kind of the operational
psychology of that or do people write
refle refs or do you reflect or
anticipate other than just confronting
the moment as it flows through us as we
throw flu um it what do we do with our
minds and
bodies I like I predict the next token
and then that's as far as no um yeah I
think what it is the reason it goes so
fast is
because there wasn't really too much
money in the space there was but it was
in like a very narrow Corner that was
like Mo I think most people who
are very understanding of the systems
wouldn't have engaged with or uh
otherwise didn't have the expertise to
and then when you know gbt 3.5 and gb4
and gbt2 really even to a little like a
lesser extent were starting to get a lot
of momentum and eyes on things and then
everyone's like oh I can go get 10
billion dollar you know I think that
really motivated a huge influx of cash
and there already was this like Nvidia
was already making giant models opening
IE was you know there still but the
difference like now is that because
there was money being made rather than
just spent and there's a market use case
that's become clear now the people who
are engaging with it are doing so for
cost First like reasons like they want
to reduce costs as much as they can and
improve efficiency as much as they can
it turns out that you can like if you're
not doing a formal implementation of a
new thing for the first time once to
write a paper and then throwing it away
you can actually do a lot in that front
you can really optimize everything in a
lot of directions and you know I think
also the h100s happening when they did
made giant difference h100s are quite
crazy Nvidia actually took if I recall
correctly and I may be wrong but if I am
wrong you can verify it by going and
watching the um Nvidia like keynote
where they released them in in March of
last year April and uh maybe even the
month before March um
but they took warehouses full of A1 100s
and they chocked them full of R tracing
Ai and they predicted the patterns of
all of the photons moving through this
insane ultraviolet laser they made by
turning liquid tin into Pure Energy with
a microwave disc and uh then they didn't
run into the uner principle because they
didn't measure the light they just
predicted it all and so they able to
print architecture below 2 nanometers so
that the uh you know there was no
interference
from the collapse of the waveform which
is that's all sci-fi words every single
thing in that sentence is sci-fi and so
like it's just a lot of forces at once
kind of snapping together
and efficiency though is like not I
think I think people often take
efficiency and
how good the models are now at reasoning
in like this way as progress towards AGI
or
towards Terminator or
whatever and it's not because I think
one thing unilaterally when I've like
discussed this with other people who
have uh better opinions than my own or
sometimes even like people who are just
kind of thinking about it in general
because there's a lot of really
intuitive and really smart people out
there the it's not that like it's not
about how big you can get it and how
smart it becomes and how good reasoning
it gets because that doesn't solve any
of the problems that it
currently you know there when you think
about it like if you just drop gp4 in a
McDonald's it's not selling anybody a
hamburger right like it's not even close
to selling anyone in hamburger and it's
not because it's not good at reasoning
it's because it's a it doesn't do
anything until you go touch it right
like you have to go send it something to
get something back and then it doesn't
know that the next time you send it
something and there's just all these
features that would have to be there for
something to like actually start to
exhibit this kind of
continuous live real life interacting
back and
forth like evolving that we do over time
that uh we're not even thinking about
like we're not even heading that way so
fear not I guess we're just getting
really cool tools mostly it's going to
get a lot easier to code which is going
to let you code really cool and
interesting things because you'll be
able to just kind of describe what you
want to do and walk through the logic
and not have to learn new programming
languages which is great because I don't
really don't want to have to learn
JavaScript and I think I have to learn
JavaScript I'm hoping I can just wait it
out I think that angle with the
um the language of thought and systemes
and the ability in systems modeling as
applied in artificial intelligence and
active inference and so on
for truly increasing ly if you can dream
it you can do it if you can say it that
was the composability
and the path through semantic space
that's why that person said it that way
at that time and when we can start to
have the
interfaces that support
that um we don't question that 3+ 3 on
the calculator is going to give us a
number and we already barely question
the epistemic honic treadmill so fast
barely question entering in text and
getting an
image and as that kind of meta fluidity
as the input output relationships that
our bodies from development and
evolution have become used to those
modalities are being remixed and
augmented
massively and you're totally right that
a very small inside
conversation has tremendous propagation
of causal consequences for the action
perception Loop of people who aren't
even here
today then okay can you um in what sense
so I I mean I
agree if if you're saying what I what I
what I what I've been shooting but I
feel like I'm missing a point
here when when you're referring to a
action uh reaction inside loop like like
an internal like a small conversation
being important I understand what you
mean in the sense that like yeah if
somebody needs to hear something and
just understand what we're talking about
because they don't know anything about
Ai and like it's very important then
that is this but what did you that was a
metaphor right that was an analogy or
something I think I missed that part was
it I'm talking about yeah it could have
been a fractal Dimension metaphor but
that's not how I intended it I just
meant that when these semantic
augmentation techniques are crafted
they're artific artificial intelligence
and then they're
disseminated um including their
plasticity to end users that's a level
of semantic and Intermodal
control that's just getting air dropped
on on humans who are here today and or
not
yeah no um this is actually touches on
something that's very interesting to me
uh personally because I've like watched
this happen the entire time I've been in
this space there's always been this
through line of people who are um I
weirdly like almost never AI guys
they're always like pure python guys or
pure coding
types
and it's always like the really smart
people and they're always and it's it's
it's it's specifically modeling so
social
systems at a very high rate of iteration
with AI to get work done which sounds a
lot drier than what it really is but I
don't know the good like a good way of
phrasing what's actually happening in
there it's like very interesting and
it's like it's just exploiting the
inherent structure of the way that we
communicate because we had to structure
that just to make it this
far and what's cool about it is that the
models do it and they don't know that
they're doing it and the people make the
models do it because it works and they
don't know why it worked they just do it
and all the way up to the tippy top the
only thing that's really happening is
this but fast and because it's so fast
you're processing information really
really quickly in a way that has like
this emergent quality of its own of
being more robust to creating structur
so like an example would be
um GPT engineer right or little coder or
baby AGI where it's communication
explicitly like linguistic normal back
and forth producing
work and that feels important and I
don't know there's not a word for it
really what what that type of thing is
that I
think but I was wondering what you would
what you thought about this kind of area
of well of structure one aspect seems to
be that um rather than the monolith
model which is let's see how well this
monolithic API returns um evaluations on
these on this data set instead there's
kind of a co-constructive element which
is like well the Benchmark of any of
these given nestmates in the ant colony
is not that important what's important
is like the overall architecture that
the colony creates so that that's one
aspect and then another aspect is um for
those whose work is
organizational or a facilitator or any
other things in that
area then care and
compassion is expressed through
technical means and so there's the
situations where it's a technical
ends and then there's technical means
for non-technical ends and all the other
quadrants over there too but it can
truly be the case that that
ultra um advanced techn technology can
be utilized for pro-social and for human
ends just like an engine could be used
to help people this is an information
engine and it similarly can also be used
even from its early days and phases for
that
goal that's a really interesting take I
hadn't thought about that and so there
is
like yeah so when you put it that way
it's like
yeah it is a like it's clinical when you
consider that yes our social structures
have a logic to them if you do them fast
that logic happens fast but it's it's
more interesting when you consider what
that means in terms
of humans like our expression and our
and our like the the way that the things
that we value right because like that is
important to that working so if I guess
if there is a latent fear right that
people have at the moment of getting
pushed out of whatever the economy of
the world becoming like very
technological and
dry then fear not because this stuff
works really well and I can see there's
clearly a utilitarian use case for
preserving it and uh you know it's not I
probably won't even have to convince
anyone you just have to get really fast
um it is interesting too to consider
like what if at some point our
technology I guess it really actually
kind of is becoming this weird blending
of
social stuff with rigorous
formal bits and bites you
know I have many questions on this I
mean I I think we've also talked a lot
about the outputs and the quality of the
outputs but again our experiences in
these knowledge systems are not
only outcome
oriented so if we can if we can train
models on all
dissertations and then it's possible to
one button write a
dissertation how does that change the
training environment and and
the the actual pace of Our
Lives when things
that we spent time on have just been not
just like rug pulled or accelerated but
they've been outmoded like steam engine
to gas engine
so it's like well we don't need that we
don't need that kind of fuel anymore or
we don't need that kind of construction
anymore I think um I think it's overall
a positive thing man like because you
can't there's really not a good reason
to say that we'll have less jobs right
like if you want to take it like as
broad as possible because there's no
thing that you can add more complex
stuff that's like so complex no one even
like can describe it fully in a single
sitting or tin and then it's easier to
deal with right like that just means
you're going to need more people to
handle it because like now you have more
edge cases and like your reach is
broader but you're just solving more
problems but we're not going to run out
of problems anytime soon I mean I myself
like I have a hard time thinking about
the um I have a hard time abstracting
from the input output what is the
utility why are we doing it how much you
know profit problem solve whatever it do
it do but that's because like y we are
buried in problems right now you know
there's
everyone is 100% of their day every
single day when they wake up to when
they go to sleep solving problems all
day every single day we're gonna be fine
right I think that if you really like
something and you are very much attached
to it being enabled more by AI to do it
even better and with a broader reach and
do all the cool weird stuff that you
would like needed like 50 employees to
do before is huge because you're going
to be able to do it even better and now
you're actually going to be able to give
people the thing that you have't in your
head that you were otherwise like didn't
have time to do and that's that's a big
deal to me I mean
like functionally you're never going to
have a situation where everybody in
general gets the ability to express
themselves more fully and have more of a
ability to do the things that they care
about and it's going to be worse right
like unilaterally throughout all of the
history I mean there yeah there's
education there's individuals sure and
there's there's systems and groups but
overall we did we got here right
and it it's just there's a floor right
you want to raise it and you
can so if you're worried about that if
if you're worried like what if I get
outsourced like ask
yourself what could like if you were
also really good knowing what you
already know that like probably that
many people don't know as well as you do
in your Edge in your like Niche and also
you have an AI that you know how to use
like now you're Superman right one and
then two if we don't have to work
like why would you make people right I
mean I don't think that we won't have to
work I think we're definitely have to
work it sucks I'm sorry guys but it does
at some point become a question you have
to ask otherwise like why would what are
you g to make us go to work if we don't
have to this this
sucks quickly becoming empirical and
actual are any philosophical debates
related to meaning and life and all
these big topics and I
guess current moment you have a lot of
alarms near
you yeah yeah so there was I guess some
cops going down the road there it's all
good in the current day we really have
the empirical consequences and playing
out of these debates and I guess
it's hard to feel like there's even a a
Tempo or a beat to reflect on
it and maybe that's just part of the
game that most of the Dust kicks up just
dissipates away and isn't recorded and
the footsteps are recorded but most of
the consequences of that footstep are
dissipated
away
it dude it's data right like that's
really that that's just data
like I can do a lot with data I think
that you can do a lot with
data the problem being confused I guess
by the noise and not really feeling like
you can get your bearing I mean that's I
mean that's why I'm here right like
that's what we're doing this this
podcast for I think that's what many
communities are currently activating for
and being activated around um
understanding what's happening is free
uh it's fundamentally still like large
largely a research space nobody's going
to think you're dumb where everyone is
narrow because it's so complicated so I
guess like that's one piece of advice
I'd like to part on anyone who's
watching this if you feel like you like
you want to ask questions but you don't
really want to look like dumb because
you don't really understand it's like
dude it makes no sense don't worry about
it it's really complicated I totally get
it ask questions it's it's a science
thing like it's science we like
questions it's Pol it's okay it's highly
respected you're cooler if you do ask
the question honestly because it's it's
to be able to answer them and not have
to ask them ourselves
so don't don't feel intimidated by the
space um
and we all know the internet
sucks every single one of us you know I
know everyone I work with knows everyone
you work with knows ideally we get to a
place really quickly where the only
thing you have to do is want something
and want to know
something and you just get that whatever
we have stored full and Total Access to
it without having to try and learn data
science and learn to code and all these
other things and need a bunch of
Hardware that's doable now like I could
do that today if I had you know like a
bunch of money
but overall it's if it's achievable with
what we have at this
moment then it's a foregone conclusion
the space is moving fast but it's moving
fast in a lot of ways at once so just
because you don't see movement in a
particular direction it doesn't mean
that it's going to be a huge amount of
effort to get there and it might take
years years it's really just because
everyone works on too many things and
we're all overworked and there's like
not that many people who are really
feeling like they should engage with the
space or that they can because they
didn't you know go to college or
something I worked in a vape shop you
know um you can you can definitely
handle it it's it's just
intimidating so certainly anyone who's
interested jump in it's cool it's sci-fi
like all the way down it doesn't get
boring I
promise it might get a little boring
sometimes if it does just look at one of
the other crazy sci-fi things that are
happening in this way and just go look
at that thing
inste that's that's nice I feel very
similarly about
questions the oldies are the goodies and
the basic questions are the ones that
beginners can ask and the ones that
enliven the experienced as well and it's
either a question that has been asked at
which point the answer is new to you and
its education or it's a question that
has hasn't been asked or it's been asked
but never answered and then it's
research and so it's like at the speed
of question marks you can accelerate
your own epistemic journey and or the
broader epistemic Adventure that we're
all on together by putting new questions
together and the speed is
moving faster than we can
blink which brings some new kind of
Dynamics like uh quantity has a quality
all of its own as they say but yet that
human component and the fact
that hopefully the um welcome to those
of all backgrounds can be made clear I
think is also really
positive in fact dude I don't know if
you've had this experience but I've had
this a bunch of times where somebody has
no idea what's going on they're just
like this is the coolest thing ever and
I'm involved now and you're going to
help me get there and I'm like okay
right they have the best idea like
there's people who Intuit it things that
took me months of just eating bricks to
learn and they're totally in the space
they have no idea what I'm talking about
but then they go and build something
with like basic python that's totally
new and completely shoots off in a
different direction it's because there's
really not that much that's been done um
it's all been very iterative and very
slow on many many fronts there's been a
lot done but there's a lot of ways to go
H still you can really strike out in
basically any direction and immediately
hit the wall of like oh no one's ever
tried that before okay and just try it
and find new stuff and not only that
find old stuff that we just forgot about
because there's so many
papers I'll make one comment and then
I'll ask a question from the live chat
it reminds me of studying ants and
loving ants in graduate school it's like
wait no one has measured humidity and
the rates of water loss in this one
species in this one Valley it's like how
can we not know when that's such a
beautiful part of
nature yeah I guess when you start at AI
you're already way specific yes okay
I'll ask some uh questions from the live
chat as we kind of head towards the end
so sure Matthew h wrote will llms
continue to lead the way in Ai and for
how long I don't think llms could ever
produce AGI am I wrong no you're
absolutely right if they do they're
going to be part of something they're
may it depends on how much money people
are really going to keep spending on him
man CU like maybe may maybe two years I
think at the
outset if it's real bad but I think
probably not that long even are we going
to be mainly focused on
llms and then what's behind that
Vista I don't know something else like
something cheaper problem with llms is
like they will they cost quadratically
more the longer your contact length the
more weights you have like every single
direction of improvement is almost
always just a million times more dollars
you had one thing and now it costs you
know as much as everything else plus one
like again
so that alone I think is plenty of
reason to say that this Ain this ain't
it but also because it's too simple I
think systems make more sense than
blobs I'll just mention one kind of
active inference recent advances for the
planning capacities also that kind of
exponential poal computational
complexity was experienced like to go
from a plan of length 10 to 11 there's a
blow up just like chess playing however
recently is it uh yeah however um
recently with some work on Direct policy
inference now it's possible to have
linear increases so that making a plan
of 11 steps versus 10 it's only 10% more
computationally intensive which is kind
of closer to how it feels in terms of
like 11 ft being 10% longer than 10 ft
and so that is um a really exciting way
that potentially some of that planning
explosion but that's not the whole
that's not everything it's not that
exact combinatoric explosion but what is
what's a what's a quadratic today could
be linear tomorrow and all of a sudden
new categories of possibilities appear I
think that's absolutely true and also
phenomenal um and
also it's still not enough I think like
even linear like if you're going token
wise linear is like real hard to make
work man I hit a million tokens like in
the last couple hours you know what I
mean um I think oh that's
cool uh yeah no I don't have any
comments though because I'm I'm not uh
I'm going to just talk dumb stuff about
active entrance from the place of I
don't know what you were referring to as
far as like this most recent advancement
but now I want to know we we'll explore
we'll Explore More I think like I guess
sort of as we
close there's so many things I'm curious
about but I'm going to ask something
that just is what is on top of Mind how
do you
physically structure your setup and your
approach with just the choices of uh
what to do with the one of
you what like how do you choose what to
do with a one of you as you have the
visibilities to spin up all of these
symbolic kind of
emissions like what's really the
positive and
[Music]
guiding reminder or I'm not sure I'm
just wanting to know the human
side I don't know that's a question
that's like either I can be honest and
we can go on for another three or four
more hours um I might
cry or I can be uh more honest and say I
just like cool stuff and like sci-fi is
pretty neat and I'm like I'm okay math
so like it just kind of falls into place
a little bit and so I think really yeah
I just I I think that it's a human right
this whole AI thing I think that we
should just enable people man that's it
that's really my whole message I came
here with today is like it's cool and
you should have
access okay I'll ask a closing question
and then your answer can be your your
closing thought upcycle Club wrote do
you have any insights on emerging Trends
in open source AI
development yeah dog
um oh man what is like emerging Trends
in what context so like are we talking
about dude it's all emerging Trends the
whole thing is emerging really really
fast like in in a bunch of different
directions I think we're going to graphs
I think we're going to reinforcement
learning I think time series models are
going to be really really important
really soon I think Transformers suck
but I think we're going to keep using
them for a
while I think we're going to get
probably like some gigantic that's going
to run really efficiently because of all
this like one bit 68 bit stuff that came
out about quantization but like that's
probably not going to get used a whole
lot because what they don't say when
they talk about this stuff is that you
then have to go write kernels if you
want to use it in your company and no
one knows how to write Cuda kernels
except for like a couple people who cost
a lot of money so in general yeah a lot
of trends like all the time
well thank you for
72.1 we can come back and maybe see a
little bit of generativity little bit of
active inference and um thank you for
for engaging and I look forward to next
time yep absolutely thanks a bunch man
bye